Hi, in the previous video, we've seen how to compute the cardinal spline and
the cardinal spline was an interpolation spline that was going through every data point
But we've noticed that at best we could have only a C1 continuity and we could not have a C2 continuity
What we will study today is the uniform cubic B spline
Which is an approximation curve because we won't go through the data point
But at this time it will actually give us a C2 continuity
So, we'll see how to compute a uniform cubic B-spline using the DeBoer algorithm.
And the DeBoer algorithm is fairly simple to use.
The stuff that you have to do is if you have a bunch of points and you want to fit a curve
through it, the first step is to split every edge in three.
So, you have equidistance points now on those lines.
Now that we have those, we could actually
start to connect the last and the first one,
and then the last and the first, the last and the first,
and so on and so on.
And once you've done this, we could
start to split each of those new edges in half.
So you have a point in the middle now every time.
Now that we have those points, what we could do
is to use those four points we have here
and give them inside of a basic curve,
saying that that's a cubic-basic curve we want to build here.
And then we can give the next four points to the next cubic-basic curve.
And that's how you actually build a uniform cubic base plane.
Now it has the advantage that it has computed for us.
Those dungeons make sure that the points on each side
were equidistant and on the same line.
So actually, we've done all the stuff that we said
that was annoying to do in the basic curve
when we stick them back to back.
And by doing so in this way
and making sure that we have the points in the proper place,
what happened is that we have a C2 continuity.
So if I re-draw this exact same curve here,
you could see now that my first derivative is continuous
And my second directive is also continuous, so I have continuity in C1, C0, C1 and C2.
Now at the same way we've computed the cardinous plane using Hermit curves and then we decided
to try to find the mathematics to be able to compute directly cardinous plane without
the need of going through Hermit curves.
We could do the same for Uniform Cubic Spline.
Instead of having a function that will give us all the points
that we have to give to basic half to compute those,
we can actually find a formula that will allow us
to directly compute a Uniform Cubic B Spline.
And this algorithm is the Cox-DeBoer basis.
It's a bit like going from the basic half
using the Castellge algorithm to the Bernstein basis.
Now we're going from the Bohr algorithm
to the Cox-DeBohr basis.
And how it works is an iterative process
to build those base.
And it's a bit tricky to understand,
maybe if I just show you the mathematics.
It's an iterative function that starts
with the simplest step,
and I will show you here mathematically.
So the way the Cox-DeBord basis start,
it says that it has a bunch of knots.
So that's your points you want to have.
And in this case, because I'm using the cubic version,
what I want to have is basically four knots,
meaning that I have five points, let's say.
And what happened is I have a point at zero at one,
two, three, and four, for instance.
And that gives me four different curves.
And the curves see, and they're just on and off.
And that's what the definition is here.
It says that if I have a basis of degree zero for index i,
it says the value is one if my t value
that goes between, in this case, zero to five,
or zero to four, sorry.
If my T value is bigger than the knots before and smaller than the knots after, actually
I'm 1, otherwise I'm 0.
And that's what you can see here.
I have my first base, which is the blue line.
The blue line is 1, and I drop at 0s, and then I get the yellow, and then I get the
green, and then I get the red.
So I get four different curves that just on and off.
And then if you want to start to compute a higher degree,
it's an iterative recursive function.
So basically it says that you take the level,
the base before and with the index i, index i plus one,
and you do basically a linear interpolation,
which is a bit more complex now
because we have range and all that kind of stuff,
but that's what those two functions here are doing.
do linear interpolation between the different bases and so meaning that we started from the four
different base now we have three base that blue triangle is the interpolation between the blue
square and the yellow square the yellow triangle is the yellow and green and the green triangle
is the green and red and then you can go one higher step and then you can interpolate
between the two triangles, which give you that nice curves, and then you can interpret between
the two curves and that you get one big curve. And that gives me my final answer, that's the curve
I'm interested in to try to compute my uniform cubic B-spline. Bit abstract at this point still,
so what I will do is that I will redo exactly the same mathematics as the one I've done here,
accept that this time I will do them symbolically so I can compute them and see the mathematics
behind that nice curve I have here. And so this is exactly the same formula I've computed except
that I've solved it and asked it to collect for my different points, my different bays basically.
so I get base 1, base 2, base 3. And that's the formula for this curve, right? So again,
you can see that my first base is multiplied by a bunch of t's and all that kind of stuff,
as we've had the habit to see most of the time. And if I turn them in four different
base so I really have my first base here the function is t the t cube divided by
six so I get t cube divided by six give them four different functions and I
give them the the proper range you see I have the curve as we have here except
that now I have colored them in the four different pieces I had so I have a piece
between 0 and 1 and 1, 2, 2, 3, 3 and 4. But that gives me that nice curve.
And so now that I have this, basically what I want to do is instead of having
that nice curve that goes between 0 and 4, I want to bring that back between 0 and 1.
And I basically don't want to squish the curve itself. What I want to do is I want to slide
each piece of them to to bring them back to between zero and one so I have my blue between
zero and one I want to move the yellow between zero and one the green between zero and one
and the red between zero and one and that's what I do here I take the function I had upstairs
except that I'm substituting t with t plus one t plus two t plus four to slide them
and that's the the different functions you will have now so t cube hasn't moved so my
my first one hasn't moved the other one it's a bit different than before
and what happened is that if I use this as the four different functions now we could see
that I have what I wanted I basically have the four bases right on top of each other between zero
and one and it's basically as the one we had with with the Bernstein bases I mean the sum of
of all of those curves is always equal to one.
No matter where we are between zero and one.
That's the advantage of those bases.
So it's a basis the same way within the Bernstein basis.
It's just different shape.
So that will allow us to do a bit of different things.
So what we can do is that we could use those four different
bases and multiply them by the different points
wanted to use. So you have 0.0, 0.1, 0.2 and 0.3. The four different points will be multiplied by
the four different bases basically the same way within the basic curve. And so what we do is we
take the the the the one we shifted the most on the left. So basically 0.3 is my first base
then point two is my second point one is my third and point zero is my fourth
and I can turn this into a matrix form as I usually do so what we have is all my
mathematics into the matrix form I've just put the divided by six here in front because it's
It's basically everything is divided by six all the time.
And so that's the B-spline segment now.
It's just a matrix form again,
and just a multiplication of one matrix.
And I can compute a B-spline
by just moving back to back a bunch of points.
And then we could see that if I render this again,
directly I have now the same curve
I had before, except that I'm not doing the split linear computing or that kind of stuff,
giving that to the basic curve. I'm just directly using my matrix to generate this.
And the same way we've done with the card in the spline, you know, if we wanted to actually
start at the first point and that kind of stuff. If we want to do the same, basically we actually
have now to repeat it two times. So you have to put the first point three times and the last point
three times and if you do this you have a curve that starts at point zero and ends at point one.
And so this is how you compute the uniform cubic B spline and that will be the last type of spline
we will study in these videos because I have most of what we will probably encounter when we do
animations. If later we need to go through a different type of curves, because there is
still other curves, other splines, we will see if we need to make a new video. But for now,
that will be the last type of curve we want to see. And in the next video, what we will see
is how we could use those curves to actually encode animation data. See you next time.